John Charles Frémont and Jessie Benton Frémont Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
John Charles Frémont and Jessie Benton Frémont Papers 1828-1980 (bulk 1835-1890)
MSS1459
Frémont, John Charles, 1813-1890; Frémont, Jessie Benton, 1824-1902
1,000 items
9 containers plus 1 oversize and 1 artifact
9 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Explorer of the western United States, army officer, and politician (John Charles Frémont). Author (Jessie Benton Frémont). Correspondence, presidential campaign material from 1856, Civil War items, writings, prints, photographs, and printed matter relating to the careers of both John Charles Frémont and Jessie Benton Frémont.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Beecher, Henry Ward, 1813-1887--Correspondence.; Bok, Edward William, 1863-1930--Correspondence.; Frémont, Jessie Benton, 1824-1902. John Charles Frémont and Jessie Benton Frémont papers. 1828-1980.; Frémont, John Charles, 1813-1890.; Johnson, Robert Underwood, 1853-1937--Correspondence.; Kern, Richard H., 1821-1853. Richard H. Kern diary. 1848-1849.; Park, T. W. (Trenor William), 1823-1882--Correspondence.; Poinsett, Joel Roberts, 1779-1851--Correspondence.; Waring, George E. (George Edwin), 1833-1898.
Organizations
United States. Army. Mountain Department.; United States. Army. Western Department.
Subjects
Presidents--United States--Election--1856.
Places
United States--Discovery and exploration.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--Politics and government--1853-1857.; West (U.S.)--Description and travel.; West (U.S.)--Discovery and exploration.
Titles
John Charles Frémont papers
Occupations
Army officers.; Authors.; Explorers.; Politicians.
Provenance
The papers of John Charles Frémont and Jessie Benton Frémont were acquired by the Library of Congress through purchase in 1903 and 2011 and by transfer in 1930.
Transfers
Some prints and photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division where they are identified as part of the John Charles Frémont and Jessie Benton Frémont papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of John Charles Frémont and Jessie Benton Frémont papers are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
John Charles Frémont (1813-1890) first gained public attention through his participation in and eventual leadership of scientific and mapping expeditions in the American West (1838, 1841, 1842, 1843, and 1845). In 1841 he married Jessie Ann Benton (1824-1902), the daughter of Senator Thomas Hart Benton of Missouri, who was an advocate of United States expansion into the West and a political supporter of his son-in-law's expeditions, which received Congressional backing. Jessie Benton Frémont assisted in the writing of her husband's 1844 expedition report, which enjoyed popularity with the general public, and with his subsequent writings. During his final expedition, Frémont became involved in California's uprising against Mexico. He was appointed military governor of California, but later was arrested and court-martialed in Washington, D.C., in 1847-1848 for disobedience. His penalty was set aside by President James K. Polk and he and Jessie moved to California in 1849. They became wealthy after the discovery of gold on their Las Mariposas land grant. In 1850, Frémont was elected senator from the new state of California and served briefly in that office. He ran as the first presidential candidate of the Republican party in 1856 on a free-soil anti-slavery platform. He served as a Union general in the Department of the West during the Civil War. Frémont was governor of the Arizona terrritory, 1878-1883. He died in New York City in 1890. The Frémonts suffered economic reversals and in later years were supported primarily through Jessie Benton Frémont's writings. During the 1870s through the 1890s she authored books, stories, and many articles that appeared in leading magazines. She died in Los Angeles, California, in 1902.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of John Charles Frémont (1813-1890) and Jessie Benton Frémont (1824-1902) span the years 1828-1980 with the bulk of the material dating from 1835 to 1890. The collection includes correspondence, presidential campaign material from 1856, Civil War items, writings, prints, photographs, printed matter, and books. Throughout the collection are typed transcripts of letters, lists of items, and occasional typed descriptions of items. These were not created by the Library of Congress but came with the collection and have been retained as supplemental information.
The Civil War file contains no items written by John Charles Frémont. Some letters are addressed to Frémont as commander in charge of the Western Department and the Mountain Department. Other items are related to his command during the war or are addressed to Major George E. Waring who took over his command in Missouri. Before and after the war, Waring was a prominent sanitary engineer and civic reformer, leading projects such as the engineering of the drainage system for New York's Central Park.
The correspondence consists mainly of letters sent by Jessie Benton Frémont and John Charles Frémont. All but five letters are written by the Frémonts. The Jessie Benton Frémont correspondence includes many letters to Robert Underwood Johnson and Edward William Bok. A lengthy run of letters to T. W. (Trenor William) Park in the John Charles Frémont correspondence primarily concerns the Frémont's California property. Other notable correspondents include Henry Ward Beecher and Joel Roberts Poinsett.
The presidential campaign of 1856 material includes pamphlets supporting and opposing Frémont, songbooks, and graphic material. The printed matter contains both items written by the Frémonts and items written about them. The book collection, part of the printed matter file, includes items authored by the Frémonts. The books remain unorganized in four record center cartons. A list of contents is in each box. Other items in the collection include engravings, prints, photographs, legal papers, printed matter, and a dispatch box.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material and chronologically therein, except for the Civil War file, which is arranged alphabetically.
Container List
- Civil War file (Box 1)
  - List of contents (Box 1)
  - A-W, 1860-1864 See also Oversize, (5 folders) (Box 1)
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Frémont, Jessie Benton (Box 1)
    - List of contents (Box 1)
    - 1840-1902, undated, (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Frémont, John Charles (Box 1)
    - List of contents (Box 1)
    - 1835-1863, (7 folders) (Box 1)
    - 1864-1889, undated, (5 folders) (Box 2)
- "Diary of Richard H. Kern, a Member of John C. Frémont's Expedition, Oct. 20, 1848-Feb. 16, 1849" (Box 2)
- Dispatch box inscribed with Frémont name and letter concerning provenance of box, 1973, undated See also Container VA 1, Artifact, Dispatch box (Box 2)
- Engravings, prints, and photographs (Box 2)
  - Frémont, Jessie Benton, circa 1890-circa 1905 (Box 2)
  - Frémont, John Charles, circa 1850-circa 1862, circa 1890, 1956 (Box 2)
- Newspaper clippings, 1884-1890, 1972 (Box 2)
- Legal papers, 1828, 1854-1868, 1875, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Miscellany, 1889, 1901, 1935, 1950, undated (Box 2)
- Presidential campaign of 1856 (Box 2)
  - Graphic material, 1856 See also Oversize (Box 2)
  - Miscellany, 1856 (Box 2)
  - Opposing Frémont, 1856 (Box 2)
  - Songbooks, 1856 (Box 2)
  - Supporting Frémont, 1856, 1864 (Box 3)
- Printed matter (Box 3)
  - Biographical material about John Charles Frémont, 1848-1862, 1903, circa 1910, 1980, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Circle of friends of the medallion, honoring John Charles Frémont, 1913 (Box 3)
  - Cora O'Kane; or, The Doom of the Rebel Guard, 1868 (Box 3)
  - House of Representatives documents, 1847-1848, 1862 (Box 3)
  - "Letter from Col. Benton to the People of Missouri," 1853 (Box 3)
  - Mariposa estate, California, 1863-1873 (Box 4)
  - Plantæ Frémontiane; or, Descriptions of Plants Collected by Col. J. C. Frémont in California, 1853 (Box 4)
  - Reports of the governor of Arizona, 1878-1879, 1895 (Box 4)
  - Senate documents (Box 4)
    - California claims, 1848-1856, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - "Conquest of California" by J. R. Thomson, 1850 (Box 4)
    - Court martial, 1848 (Box 5)
    - Expedition reports, 1843, 1854 (Box 5)
    - "Geographical Memoir upon Upper California" by John Charles Frémont, 1848 (Box 5)
  - Unarranged books (Rc 1-4)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Civil War file, A-W, Rosters and charts of the 4th Regiment Cavalry, Missouri Volunteers, 1863-1864 (Container 1) (Box OV 1)
  - Presidential campaign of 1856, Graphic material, "Grand National Republican Banner," 1856 (Container 2) (Box OV 1)
- Artifact, Dispatch box inscribed with Frémont name, undated (Container 2) (Box VA 1)